Give me a grape.
葡萄
The biggest one.
大的 最大的那顆
Give me a date.
棗
Why is it so noisy there?
什麼這麼熱鬧
Suddenly there was a loud bang.
忽聽得轟隆一聲巨響
Guess what?
你們猜 怎麼著
What's up?
怎麼著 怎麼著
There was an explosion in the mine.
礦炸了
The Third Princess saw it.
三公主見狀
She rushed to the exit.
立馬衝到出口
She began to remove the stones by hand
徒手刨開石塊
to save the people below.
要救下面埋的眾人
It was not long before
沒過多久
Lin Qi, along with her family,
林七帶著眾家人
hurried to the scene.
匆匆忙忙地趕到
Lin Qi
這林七
had been at odds with the Third Princess since childhood.
打小和三公主就不太對付
Now,
現如今
she saw the Third Princess had destroyed her family's black stone mine.
看到三公主毀了自家的烏石礦
She got very furious.
她這火冒三丈
Would she let it go easily?
她能善罷甘休嗎
Definitely not.
那肯定不能
No.
不能呀
Yeah.
就是
Lin Qi gnashed her teeth and said:
這林七咬牙切齒地說道
"Whoever kills the Third Princess will get huge reward."
給我誅殺三公主 重重有賞
Huge reward?
重重有賞
Do you know
你們猜這個時候
what the Third Princess was doing at that time?
三公主在幹什麼
What?
幹什麼
She took no notice of Lin Qi's words
三公主依然不聞不聽地
and still kept removing the stones like crazy.
在拼命地挖著石塊
Her ten fingers were bleeding heavily
只見她的雙手十指
with her skin cut open and flesh torn.
是皮開肉綻 血肉模糊 鮮血淋漓
You could even see the bones inside.
手指的骨頭都露了出來
The knuckles were also disjointed.
手指節 也紛紛掉落
But she didn't stop.
但她依然沒有停下來
She kept removing the stones.
挖著石塊
She was intent on saving all the people.
一心想要救眾人
Just at the critical moment when Lin Qi and everyone surrounded the Third Princess
就在林七帶著眾人圍著三公主
and were about to kill her,
要痛下殺手的危急關頭
luckily, Young Master Han was by her side
幸好有韓少君
and protected her.
在三公主身旁保護著她
Wearing a plain blue topcoat
韓少君一身青衣素羅袍
and holding a Breeze Sword in hand,
手拿清風劍
Young Master Han was like a real killer
猶如殺神一般
with awe-inspiring looking and bellicose presence.
那是威風凜凜 殺氣騰騰
With him guarding a place,
真的是一人當關
even ten thousand people could not get through.
萬夫莫開之勇
Great.
好
He wielded the sword, all the people fell to the ground.
手中劍一揮 萬人倒地
Blood flowed like a river.
頓時是血流成河
Wherever his sword went,
劍光所至
all living creatures
血肉之軀
became dead bodies.
紛紛化為白骨
It was like a living hell.
如人間煉獄一般
Why was Young Master Han so powerful?
為何韓少君如此了得
Who was his teacher and where was he from?
他師承何門 又來自何裡
If you want to learn more,
欲知後事如何
please listen to the next chapter.
咱們下回書接著分解
Tell us more.
再講講啊 先生
Yeah. Tell us more. I want to hear it.
就是 再講講啊 正想聽呢
Let me eat it myself.
我自己吃
Is it good?
好吃嗎
I also want it.
那我也想吃
Do you want it?
你想吃
Not for you.
不給
So sweet.
挺甜的
You want me to eat this?
你就給我吃這個
It's enough. It'll be a waste of food if you cannot finish it off.
足夠了 吃不了浪費
There was merely an explosion in our family's mine.
我們家不就炸了個礦嗎
Why do I have to be treated like this?
怎麼就到這步田地了
Lady, I know that
小姐 我眼看著
you and the Third Princess have been fighting with each other since childhood.
你跟三公主從小打到大
Even though you've never won in all these years,
雖然這麼多年來從來沒贏過
you just ended up breaking something or losing some money.
可也就是砸點東西 賠點錢
It was no big deal.
沒多大損失
But since the Third Princess got married,
可自從三公主成婚之後
she was like getting God's help.
她如有神助
Lady, look at this account book.
小姐 你看看這本賬簿
It's all in the red.
全是赤字
It's all caused by the Third Princess.
全是被三公主攪和的
Our family has lost
咱們家
the Music and Dance Academy and the mine.
接連折損了教坊司和礦山
Now, we have only the restaurant to barely get by.
眼下 就剩下酒樓堪堪維持了
Lady, you'd better
小姐 您往後
live a more frugal life later.
還是儉省些吧
Chen Qianqian...
這個陳芊芊
Blew up the fortune lode,
炸福脈
saved the miners,
救礦工
found the black water mine
發現黑水礦
and solved her own problem.
解開自己的難題
Suddenly, the story has taken a new twist.
情急之下 峰迴路轉
What a drama!
一出好戲呀
But none of these things were done by the heroine.
不過這些事都不是女主角做的
Had I known it, I would have persuaded Chuchu to do more,
早知道我當時就多勸勸楚楚了
which could have brought more credit to her
這還能給她功績上多記上一筆
and made it more possible
那城主之位
for her to be the City Owner.
不就踏實多了
At that time, your life was in dire danger.
當時 你性命攸關
But you were still thinking about other person's credit.
還惦記著別人的功績
Pei Heng.
裴恆
I have just said that I would express my gratitude personally to you.
我還說當面去謝謝你呢
I didn't expect you to come.
沒想到 你就來找我了
The other day,
當日還是
it was you who took me out.
你帶我出去的呢
There is no need for us to say thank you to each other.
你我之間 不必言謝
Qianqian.
芊芊
Now, everyone holds you
如今百姓對你
in deep respect.
多是景仰之情
You deserve to be the Third Princess.
你當得起三公主這個身份
There're so many people saying it
大家都這麼說
that I feel embarrassed.
我都害羞了
Many people?
都
Who else?
還有誰
Han Shuo?
韓爍嗎
The other day I saw Han Shuo step forward bravely to protect you.
那日見韓爍挺身護你
For the first time I admired men from Xuanhu City.
我第一次羨慕玄虎城的男子
They can learn literary knowledge, practice Kung Fu and lead troops in a battle.
能習文 習武 帶兵打仗
In times of crisis,
危難之際
they can
可以護在
step forward to protect their women.
自己的女人身前
It doesn't matter that you don't practice Kung Fu.
不會武功算什麼
I don't practice Kung Fu.
我也不會武功啊
What's more,
再說了
it's not that only those who practice Kung Fu
又不是隻能會武功的人
can lead troops in a battle.
才能帶兵打仗
Pei Heng, do you believe me?
裴恆 你相信我嗎
Believe you in what?
信你什麼
I have a hunch that
我有預感
in the future you will be a
我預感未來你會是一個
famous leader of the City Guards,
赫赫有名的護城軍統領
taking on the mantle of Minister of Defense Pei.
繼承已故裴司軍的衣缽
Minister of Defense?
司軍
But in Huayuan City,
可花垣城
there has never been a man who became Minister of Defense.
從未有過男子當司軍的先例
Whatever you do, there'll be the first time.
這凡事都有第一次
Why can't you be the first one?
你為什麼就不能是那第一人呢
What's more,
再說了
although you are a man,
你以男子之身
you have taken the position of Minister of Education.
已經就任了司學一職
It's unprecedented in history.
史無前例
One's prospect is not related to his gender.
前程無關性別
Not related to his gender?
無關性別
It's just like when you were saving those miners
就如同 你救那些礦民
you didn't consider whether the people below
從未想過埋在底下的人
was a man or a woman.
是男是女
Yes.
沒錯
No wonder after Her Majesty resumed your identity,
怪不得城主恢復你的身份
she asked me to oversee your learning.
還囑咐我監督你溫書
She places great hopes on your Crown Princess Election.
她對你的少城主擢考寄予厚望
Qianqian.
芊芊
If you get the first place in the Crown Princess Election
你如果中了擢考的魁首
and become the Crown Princess,
成為少城主
you can surely take on great responsibilities of all common people.
一定能肩負起這天下蒼生
After making such a scene,
這都鬧了這麼大一出了
I still cannot avoid Crown Princess Election.
怎麼還是沒有躲過少城主擢考啊
No. I won't go.
不行 我不去
I won't take the test.
我棄考了
Do not fall short of everyone's expectations.
不要辜負了百姓對你的期望
I think that those people who made me offer sacrifice to Heaven
那群讓我去祭天的人
are the same ones as those
跟現在讓我去考少城主擢考的人
who now want me to join Crown Princess Election.
就是同一批人吧
No matter which I choose, offering sacrifice to Heaven or joining the Crown Princess Election,
考試跟祭天
they don't want me to feel good.
都是不想讓我好過
Better late than never.
亡羊補牢 為時不晚
I'll help you get the first place in the election.
我一定助你 拔得頭籌
But I don't have the least intention of being the Crown Princess.
可是我一點都不想當少城主
There are so many books.
這麼 這麼多
Han Shuo, you don't need to come.
韓爍 你來湊什麼熱鬧
Be careful.
當心
It is related to the Third Princess' future.
事關三公主前程
Minister Pei...
裴司學
Even an outsider like Minister Pei comes to help you.
裴司學一個外人都來了
I am the male owner of Yueli Mansion.
我身為月璃府的男主人
Without doubt,
自然是
I must help her.
自然不能缺席
Qianqian.
芊芊
The character has been wrongly written.
字寫錯了
Which one?
哪個字寫錯了
This one.
這個字
It should be like this.
就是這麼寫的呀
Now when I write a stroke on your back,
我寫一筆
you write the same one on the paper.
你跟著我寫一筆
Okay, done.
好了好了
(Respectful form of you)
這回對了
"Ni(you)" should be above "Xin(heart)" (A pun, also means you are in my heart.)
是你在我心上
Well, you'd better
行了 你趕緊
help me with my homework immediately.
趕緊輔導我功課吧
Qianqian.
芊芊
I studied
我研究了一下
all the literary test paper of Crown Princess Election
歷屆少城主擢考的文試試卷
and found some regular patterns in it.
總結出一些規律
On this basis,
在這個基礎上
I drafted some test questions
擬了一些試題
and made comments on them.
題冊 我都幫你做了批註
If you have any question,
如有不解之處
make sure to ask me.
定要記得來向我詢問
Recently, you should resist the temptation to play.
近日 就收收你那貪玩的性子
The literary test is the first part of the Crown Princess Election.
文試 是少城主擢考的首輪比試
You can't afford to be careless.
萬萬不可大意呀
So many questions!
三年高考五年模擬
It seems that Minister Pei does not know Qianqian very well.
看來裴司學不是很瞭解芊芊
There are so many questions here.
這麼多試題
She won't try to answer these questions,
別說是做
nor will she even take a look at them.
就連看她都不會看
It's good that I also looked through
好在我也略微研究了
all the literary test paper of the Crown Princess Election.
歷年少城主擢考考題
I also found some regular patterns
總結出一些規律
and drafted some test questions.
也擬了一些試題
But they are all in this slim volume.
不過只有薄薄這一冊
These questions are all carefully chosen.
都是精選題目
If you memorize all the questions in it,
只要背過這一本
you can easily pass the test.
就能輕鬆應對考試
You carefully chose these questions.
你這勾畫的重點
Are you predicting the test questions or are you simply revealing the questions?
是透題還是押題啊
Tell me the truth.
老實交代
Did you get these questions illegally,
是不是採取了一些非法手段
like, if discovered, you would be sent to prison?
抓起來關三年的那種
You can rest assured that
你放心好了
if you study this book carefully,
學會這一本
you will surely pass the test.
保過
Young Master Han, I think you are overconfident.
韓少君未免太過自信了吧
You know that
你既然知道
this test is related to Qianqian's future
此事關係到芊芊的前途
and she should never be too careless when dealing with it.
萬不可大意
Then you should urge her
還是催著她
to spend more time on it.
多看一些才是
Yes.
是
If time permits, she can take her time.
穩妥也得在時間允許的情況下
But it's less than ten days before the Crown Princess Election.
現在距離少城主擢考不足十日
Do you think she has the ability to
你覺得以她的腦子
memorize so many questions?
能背過那麼多嗎
If she can't,
背不過
all your efforts are in vain.
都是徒勞
Let's not get personal here.
不要人身攻擊啊
I have a good brain.
我腦子好使得很
Qianqian.
芊芊
Why don't you memorize the questions in this volume today
不如 咱們今天就背過這一本
and prove that to Young Master Han?
證明給韓少君看
What Young Master Han said makes sense.
韓少君所言極是
I haven't got much brain.
我腦子確實不夠
Minister Pei.
裴司學
You missed the mark.
失策了
It turns out that I know Qianqian better.
還是我比較瞭解芊芊
I grew up with Qianqian
我與芊芊
since childhood.
自幼一起長大
She is being self-deprecating.
她 這是在自謙
I've been married with her for many days.
我與她成婚多日
She is very different from
她與從前
who she was before.
大有不同
I don't think...
大有不同倒
Why do you think that
你怎麼知道
the person you know
你瞭解的她
is real "her"?
是真正的她
Whether the person is real "her" or not,
是不是真正的她
I will have time to figure it out.
我也有時間慢慢了解
Don't bother yourself about it.
不勞裴司學費心
Qianqian.
芊芊
(Qingfeng Tea House)
二郡主 三郡主
Guess who can win?
看誰能贏
Make a bet now.
押了押了啊
Once you bet, keep your hands off the table.
買定離手啊
The Second Princess, the Third Princess.
二郡主 三郡主
Get out of my way.
讓讓 讓讓 讓讓
The Second Princess or the Third Princess?
二郡主還是三公主
The Third Princess is kind and intelligent.
三公主善良聰慧
She must be a good City Owner.
肯定是個賢明的城主
She can write script for storytelling.
還會寫話本
She has a sense of affection, loyalty and responsibility.
有情 有義 有擔當
Who are you betting on?
你們到底押誰啊
We will surely bet on
我們當然買
Your Highess.
二郡主
Give me a receipt.
開單 開單 開單
Excuse me,
那個
you...
你們就對
you have no confidence
你們就對三公主
in the Third Princess, do you?
一點信心都沒有啊
Are you kidding?
這話說的
Why don't you bet on her if you have confidence in her?
有信心你買呀
You'll lose a lot of money.
虧死你
Let's get out of here.
走了走了走了
Do we have to
話說我們一會兒
wait for the Third Princess to write script?
還要不要等三公主寫話本啊
We will soon get a lot of money.
馬上就變成有錢人了
We don't need to serve wealthy people anymore.
我們還伺候什麼甲方
Let's go.
咱們走
Come on.
快快快
Getting rich overnight without working.
不勞動就想一夜暴富
Is it true?
有這麼好的事
Let me see.
我去看看
Your Highness.
三公主
This is
這個
big seasoned durian-flavoured thin-skin melon seeds straight out of the oven.
剛出爐的五香榴蓮薄皮大瓜子
This pack is for you.
這一包 你的
This pack
這一包
will be given to Young Master Han as you ordered.
按你的吩咐 給韓少君
Excuse me, Miss?
大姐 問一下
Who did you bet on?
你們都是押的什麼呀
You mean the Crown Princess Election?
少城主擢考啊
This side is for the Third Princess.
這一邊是三公主的
That side is for the Second Princess.
那邊是二郡主的
You can put the stake on the one you like.
押哪兒擱哪兒
I'll bet.
我押了
There is no stake here.
這 可真是一個都沒有
The majority's view is proved to be correct.
群眾的眼睛果然雪亮
Make a bet on the Second Princess.
下注啊 押二
You will surely win.
穩賺不賠的買賣
Everyone knows that
誰不知道那個老三
the Third Princess is an ignorant naughty girl.
是個不學無術的混世魔王
Yes.
就是
Although the Third Princess made some progress
這三公主雖然長進了
and found the black water mine,
還炸出了黑水礦
the Second Princess is good at writing, Kung Fu, riding and shooting.
但二郡主文武騎射俱佳
When it comes to the Crown Princess Election,
單論少城主擢考
the Second Princess is sure to win in every aspect.
哪一項不穩操勝券
That makes sense.
說得好
I'll bet on her.
押了
Boss.
老闆
I'll bet all my money on
我賭上我全部的身家
the Second Princess Chen Chuchu.
押二郡主陳楚楚贏
Miss, a verbal statement is no guarantee. Where is your money?
姑娘 口說無憑 錢呢
Wait a second.
等一下
Zi Rui, come here!
梓銳 梓銳 快快快
Go back and
你回去
bring all the valuable things here.
把家裡所有值錢的東西全部拿來
Be quick!
快去
Your Highness, you'd better think it over.
三公主 你要三思
Don't worry.
你放心吧
After the Crown Princess Election,
等到少城主擢考完之後
we will have nice sleep and
咱倆就是睡覺睡到自然醒
amass a great wealth.
數錢數到手抽筋
Go quickly.
快去快去
I'll go right now.
我去
Be quick.
快 快點啊
Excuse me.
讓讓讓
I did see Zi Rui sneak in just now.
我剛剛明明看到梓銳溜進來了
Thank you.
謝謝 謝謝
Be sure to make a good count.
數清楚啊
I bet all my money on the Second Princess Chen Chuchu.
我全部押給二郡主 陳楚楚
Who is it?
誰 誰 誰
Han Shuo.
韓爍
Qianqian.
芊芊
How did you recognize me?
你怎麼看出我來了
I should have dressed you up.
早知道讓你也裝扮一下了
We should learn a lesson next time.
下次吸取教訓
Next time?
還有下次
No, no next time.
沒有下次 沒有下次
I'll go back quickly to study the test questions
我現在趕緊回去刷題
and prepare for the Crown Princess Election carefully.
認真地準備少城主的擢考
I won't let you and Minister Pei...
一定不辜負你和裴
Actually the person I mean is you.
主要是你
You're the most important.
最重要的就是你
I won't let you down.
一定不能辜負你對我的期望
Well.
那個
Where are the melon seeds for Young Master Han?
給韓少君準備的瓜子呢
Look, I went out
你看 我跑出來
especially to buy melon seeds for you.
是專門給你買瓜子的
Don't blame me.
你可別怪我
That's not true.
太假了
The Third Princess
你們三公主
is obviously fooling Young Master Han.
明明就是在哄騙我們少君
No, she isn't.
才不是呢
This is specially prepared for Young Master Han.
這是我們特意給少君準備的
Now I'm gonna go back and
那我就現在回去
review my lessons carefully.
認真地複習了
Bye-bye.
拜拜
Excuse me. Make some room for us.
來來來 騰個地兒
Even out the stakes between them.
把賬面扳平
Even out the stakes?
扳平
Chuchu.
二姐
Chuchu. I'm coming.
二姐 我來了
The tea house is having a bet on the Crown Princess Election.
茶館拿少城主擢考押注一事
Do you know that?
你可知道
Yes, I do.
知道
You have just regained your position as a princess
你剛恢復了郡主身份
and became popular among people because of the mine disaster.
又因礦難一事大獲民心
Why did you bet on me?
你為何要押我贏
Do you really have no confidence in yourself?
你就當真對自己一點信心都沒有
Chuchu, look at me. Who am I?
二姐 你看看我是誰
I am Qianqian,
我是那個從小惹禍
who has kept causing trouble day and night since childhood.
一天到晚都沒消停過的陳芊芊啊
How could this kind of person like me
我這樣的人
be the Crown Princess?
怎麼當少城主
Don't look down upon yourself.
你也不必妄自菲薄
But Chuchu,
不是 二姐
these things are widely known.
這都是明擺的事啊
Chuchu, I'm expecting highly of you.
二姐 我對你可是寄予厚望
I bet all my money on you.
全部的身家都押給了你啊
You must...
你一定要
I am looking forward to making a lot of money by betting on you.
等著靠你大賺一筆呢
Do you really think so?
你真這麼想
Definitely.
當然了
Not only me,
而且不止是我
mother must think so too.
母親肯定也是這麼想的
Mother is usually strict with you.
母親雖然平日對你嚴格
That's because she expects highly of you.
那是因為對你寄予厚望
On the contrary, look at me.
相反 你看我
She doesn't have any expectation of me.
她就是對我沒有任何期待
So no matter how big the mistake I make,
所以不管我犯了什麼滔天大禍
she doesn't take that too seriously.
她都可以不放在心上
Chuchu, you're so smart.
二姐 你這麼聰明
You must be aware of
這麼簡單的道理
such a simple fact.
你一定明白的吧
If what you said is true,
如果你說的是真的
how can you explain
那我之前
I left those miners unattended?
還棄那些礦工於不顧
That's because
那是因為
at that time you were Minister of Defense.
你身為司軍嘛
You should certainly stick to what you should do.
自然是要堅守職責的
If given another chance,
若是還有一次這樣機會
you'd surely choose to save people.
你肯定 還是會選擇救人的
Right?
對吧
You'd better prepare for the Crown Princess Election
你就踏踏實實 認認真真地
in a steady and careful way.
準備少城主擢考吧
Zi Rui.
對了 梓銳
Have a look at what I brought you.
你看 我給你帶來了什麼
These are test questions predicted by various famous teachers.
這都是各家名師押的題
Chuchu, you must not fall short of
你可千萬不要辜負
my expectations of you.
我對你的厚望啊 二姐
Qianqian, you are so...
三妹 你對我真是
It doesn't matter.
別客氣
If you have exercise books
就是如果二姐有
that you have finished off,
自己已經寫完了的習題冊
you can give them to me and I'll...
能夠讓我
Exercise books I've finished off?
寫完的
I want to review them after I go back.
我回去複習複習 翻看一下
Zi Zhu.
梓竹
Chuchu, I'm gonna go.
那二姐 沒事我就先走了
Good luck!
加油
The Third Princess is getting more and more mature.
這三公主越來越會做人了
Her words sound perfectly organized.
說起話來天衣無縫
Qianqian has been innocent since childhood.
芊芊自幼單純
She was frank and rarely deceived other people.
直來直去 很少騙人
Perhaps I am narrow-minded.
也許 是我心胸狹隘了
Since childhood,
從小到大
mother has been strict about my homework.
母親就嚴查我的功課
Especially when it comes to management,
特別是經營管理之道
she taught me all that she knew.
對我傾囊相授
I didn't get the overall view of the situation,
是我一葉障目
didn't give it deep thinking
沒想到這一層
and took it out on Qianqian.
遷怒於芊芊
Every time the Third Princess
三公主每次從您這兒
took something from you,
搶走什麼東西
she did it in a secret way.
都是悄無聲息的
But you still trust her so much.
您還這麼相信她
Zi Zhu.
梓竹
Think about Young Master Han.
您想想韓少君
Her Majesty had planned to make him marry you.
城主原本有意將他許配給您
How could the Third Princess shamelessly take him away by force?
三公主憑什麼當街強搶了去
I've been taking care of Qianqian for more than ten years.
我疼愛芊芊十數年
No matter what had happened,
不管怎樣 芊芊對我
she didn't guard against me
一直是毫無防備
and always thought about things for my sake.
為我著想的
Otherwise,
不然
she wouldn't have given me these exercise books today.
她今日也不會送來這些習題冊
The Third Princess took away the exercise books
您寫完的習題冊
you have finished off.
三公主還拿走了呢
Who knows what she is plotting.
也不知道憋什麼壞呢
It doesn't matter.
無妨
Your Highness.
公主
These exercise books have been used.
你說這些習題冊人都寫完了
What are you gonna do with them?
你還要來幹嗎
You don't understand.
這你就不懂了
They are very useful.
這些可都是寶貝
Listen up,
我告訴你啊
when you see Young Master later,
一會兒回去見到少君你就說
you tell him that these are all written by me.
這些都是我寫的
Are you clear?
記住了嗎
Yes.
好
He's coming.
來了來了來了
Come on. Wake up.
快快快 快起來
Why don't you have a rest, Your Highness.
要不歇一會兒吧 太累了
No. This question is too hard.
不行 這題難
Young Master.
少君
It's you.
少君來了
These questions are done.
題我寫完了
Can I have a rest now?
現在我能休息了吧
I've been thinking for so long.
費神
What's up?
又 又怎麼了
The Crown Princess Election is around the corner.
少城主擢考開試在即
I come here to help you with the discourse on politics.
我是來幫你練習策論的
The discourse on politics?
策論
Isn't that debating?
不就是辯論嗎
Don't worry.
你放心
I have a talent for speaking.
我這嘴皮子厲害著呢
You are so confident.
三公主這麼自信啊
Why don't we have a bet?
那咱們來賭一把
On what?
賭什麼
If I win,
如果我贏了
you kiss me.
你親我一下
What if I win?
那如果我贏了呢
I kiss you.
我親你一下
You are testing me on how well I can deal with changing situation, aren't you?
這個少君是在考我的應變能力嗎
This is no kidding.
這種玩笑可不能亂開啊
Let me ask you a question.
那我先出一題啊
In Huayuan city,
在花垣城
the relationship between father-in-law and son-in-law is always hard to be settled.
翁婿矛盾由來已久
Not only can father-in-law beat and scold his son-in-law at will,
岳父不僅可以隨意打罵女婿
but he can also make the decision to divorce him.
還可以做主將他休棄
If one day
那麼如果有一天
the father-in-law is arguing with the son-in-law,
岳父與女婿發生爭執
should the son-in-law make a compromise
女婿應該是忍讓
or should he argue strongly with the father-in-law?
還是據理力爭
I think he should argue strongly.
我覺得應該是據理力爭
Isn't it like the conflicts between mother-in-law and daughter-in-law?
這不就是婆媳矛盾嗎
It's no big deal.
小意思
Since you chose the negative side,
你這 選反方是吧
I choose the positive side.
那我就選正方
I think he should make a compromise.
我覺得是應該忍讓的嘛
The conflict between father-in-law and son-in-law
這翁婿矛盾
is nothing but some trivial matters.
無非就是一些雞毛蒜皮的小事
No matter how strongly they argue with each other,
再怎麼吵
they won't get a result.
也吵不出高低之分
And even if you do get the upper hand in the conflict,
而且就算你吵贏了
you won't get much benefit.
你也沒有什麼好處
Why can't they restrain themselves a little for the sake of the family
為什麼不為了家庭能忍一忍
and make peace with each other?
都和諧一點
Actually the spouse is uncomfortable
其實你另一半夾在中間
being stuck in between.
多難受啊
That is to say,
這麼說來
if one day
如果有一天
you have an argument with my mother,
你與我母親發生了爭執
you will make a compromise for me?
你也會為了我忍讓嗎
Don't worry.
你放心
I won't let you be harmed.
我不會讓你受委屈的
And my mother will surely love
而且我喜歡的人
the one I love.
我母親一定也會喜歡
What are you talking about?
在說什麼
Well.
行吧
This time,
這一局
you win.
算你贏了
Zi Rui, I'm hungry. Let's go.
梓銳 餓了 走
He is weird.
不是 他怎麼感覺怪怪的
He is not weird.
那還能怎麼怪
Young Master Han must have fallen in love with you.
那肯定少君認準你了唄
That makes sense.
那倒也是
I'm his wife in name.
我是他名義上的妻子啊
He is afraid that Her Majesty may use our relationship to give him a hard life.
他怕城主借我來壓制他
It doesn't matter.
無妨
We'll have to split up sooner or later anyway.
反正我倆早晚都得拆夥
What are you doing?
你幹嗎
If you have something on your mind, you can talk with me.
你那個有事說事
But don't resort to violence.
你別動手啊
Young Master said
少君說
everyone in the mansion can ask Your Highness questions.
全府上下都可以向三公主提問題
I'd like to ask you
我 我想問問
whether a man who acts cute will live a good life.
真的是撒嬌男人會好命嗎
Actually.
其實
Both men and women act cute sometimes.
男女都會撒嬌的
It's no big deal.
撒嬌其實沒有什麼大不了的
It's like a lubricant.
它就像是一個 潤滑劑
Let's say there is a conflict between a man and a woman.
在男女發生矛盾衝突的時候呢
If you act cute and make a compromise,
你稍微撒一下嬌 示一下弱
showing respect for the other side
滿足了對方的面子
and gaining benefit from her,
從對方那裡獲得一些實惠之後
you'll find that the conflict is eased
你會發現矛盾減輕了
or has disappeared.
或者是消失了
So acting cute is good
所以說撒嬌對於雙方來講
for both sides.
都會有好處
A man who acts cute will live a good life.
撒嬌男人 會好命
I cannot lift it up.
人家提不動嘛
Is there a young lady who can help me?
哪位小姐姐來幫幫人家
I'm not a young lady.
我不是小姐姐
Once again?
還來
Sorry to bother you,
敢問三公主
but I'm wondering
是不是應該
could men be allowed to take the test
也讓我們男人蔘加選拔
and get an official position of some kind.
謀個一官半職
Yes.
應該
When it comes to job,
這個職場裡面
there should not be sex discrimination.
就不要搞什麼性別歧視了
Why can't a man be an official?
男子為什麼不能當官
Time to have dinner.
可以吃了
Young Master Han said
韓少君說了
only after you answer the question seriously can you begin to eat.
認真作答後才能動筷
I just want to have some food.
我就想吃個飯
But now I have to get into an argument.
我這還得辯論
Is it reasonable?
有沒有人性啊
Well.
行
I'm not gonna eat.
我不吃了
I'm not gonna eat. Is that okay?
我不吃了行吧
Young Master has good intentions.
人家少君也是好心嘛
But you...
不是 你這
Good intentions?
好心
If he had good intentions, he wouldn't have been hard on me like this.
好心這麼折磨我
I'm telling you,
我告訴你啊
I don't want to take the test.
我不想考試
I don't want to be the Crown Princess.
我不想當少城主
From now on,
從現在開始
no one is allowed to talk to me.
你們誰都別跟我說話
Leave me alone.
我要一個人靜靜
But this.
那這
Take it.
拿著
The chicken made no mistake.
這雞也沒罪
Even the rooster is at odds with me, isn't it?
是不是連雞都要跟我槓啊
Your Highness.
郡主
It's said that many people are betting on the Crown Princess Election.
聽聞 民眾都在押注少城主擢考
The Third Princess went so far as to
三公主竟把全部身家
bet all her money on the Second Princess.
都押了二郡主贏
I fully understand what she is thinking.
箇中滋味 我深有體會
She used to be arrogant by virtue of her Kung Fu.
以往她憑藉著一番武藝張揚跋扈
But now she cannot practice Kung Fu anymore.
如今卻武功盡失
The disappointment
這其中的落差
can only be understood by the person with the same experience.
只有境遇相同的人才會明白
I'm gonna visit her.
我去看看她吧
Forget about it.
罷了
It's windy outside.
外頭風大
If by any chance I catch cold
萬一受了風寒
and have a cough with lungs infected
引發咳喘 感染肺腑
or even go into a coma and cannot take medicine,
引發昏厥 湯藥不進
I'm gonna die.
就病危了
Your Highness, you're making an excuse.
大郡主 您就是在找藉口
Well, it's important to visit Qianqian.
算了 看芊芊要緊
There won't be any trouble if I wear more clothes.
我多穿點便沒事了
Young Master,
少君
I have something to tell you
我覺得有些話
and I don't want to wait any longer.
我也沒有必要要瞞你了
Just say it.
你說
Look at me.
你看著我 來
I
我
don't want to win the literacy test
不想贏文試
or the Kung Fu test
不想贏武試
or the discourse on politics.
不想贏策論
I don't want to get involved in any fight related to Crown Princess.
不想參加有關少城主的任何爭奪
Although I was not good at literary writing before,
以前我雖文論雖淺
I excelled in Kung Fu.
但是我武藝奇佳
But now
可現在呢
I'm good at nothing.
我一無是處
I'm nobody.
就是個廢人
But you
而你呢
were forcing me again and again
卻一而再再而三地
to fight against others.
逼迫我跟別人去爭奪
Do you think it is reasonable?
你這樣合適嗎
Qianqian, if you don't have a try,
芊芊 你不試一下
how do you know you won't make it?
怎麼知道自己不行
What's more, I'm here.
況且有我在
I'll come up with a foolproof plan
我一定會想出一個萬全之策
to let you win.
讓你獲勝的
Look at this.
你看
I wrote down the answers.
我把答案都寫好了
All you have to do is to bear them in your mind.
你只要記下來就行
Even if I win the literacy test,
就算贏了文試
what can it bring me?
那又如何
Can it bring me less humiliation?
能夠少一分屈辱嗎
Or can it bring me less ridicule?
能夠少一分嘲笑嗎
No, it can't.
不能
No matter how hard I try
不管我再怎麼努力
and how much effort I make,
再怎麼勤奮
I'm still a worthless person,
我都只是一個廢人
a fat worthless person who is ridiculed by the whole world.
一個受盡天下恥笑的胖廢人
I see.
我明白了
Your Highness, don't take it personally.
郡主 你可千萬別往心裡去啊
The Third Princess
三公主這話
was talking about herself.
是 是在說她自己呢
Let's go.
我們走吧
But what she said makes sense.
可她說得沒錯
How does a worthless person
一介廢人
have the nerve to run for the Crown Princess Election?
有什麼顏面去參加擢考呢
Even if I win the literacy test and the discourse on politics,
即便是贏了文試 策論
will that change the latter half of my life?
我的後半生就會改變嗎
Am I able to stand up again?
我就能夠重新站起來嗎
Your Highness.
郡主
Mr. Su.
蘇公子
Zi Nian.
梓年兄
Minister Pei asked me to
我奉裴司學之命
ask why Her Highness
來詢問為何大郡主
was absent from class for no reason these days.
這兩日無故缺課
Her Highness is in no mood to study.
大郡主這幾日無心學習
Why?
為何
It's all because of the Third Princess.
還不是都怪三公主
Not only did she give herself up,
她自己自暴自棄就算了
but she had set a bad example and make Her Highness follow suit.
還非要捎帶上我們大郡主
Would you please deliver a message to Her Highness?
那還麻煩梓年兄幫忙通傳一聲
Tell Her Highness that
就和大郡主說
I came here to visit her.
我來看望她
Your Highness.
蘇沐見過大郡主
Your Highness. The garden overflows with the beauty of spring.
大郡主 你看這滿園春色
Let me
不如
accompany Your Highness to have a walk.
蘇沐陪大郡主出去走走
Don't bother.
不必了
No matter how beautiful it is,
風景再好
it will decline sometime.
也有衰敗的一天
I don't want the bleak sight in the future
免得以後見了蕭條的樣子
remind me of today's beauty,
想起今日盛景
thus making me feel sad.
徒增淒涼
Your Highness.
大郡主
You are kind-hearted.
你心地善良
You should see
應該看到這世間萬物
the pleasant things in the world.
美好的一面呀
As seasons alternate,
這冬去春來
even the bleakest flowers
再凋零的花
will bloom again one day.
也有重新盛開的一天
Right?
不是嗎
How did Yuanyuan overhear the words
我跟韓爍說的話
that I spoke to Han Shuo?
怎麼被長姐聽到了呢
Why?
這
Your Highness.
三公主
You're straightforward and open-minded.
你心思直爽 豁達
But Her Highness is intelligent.
可大郡主心思玲瓏啊
I'm afraid she takes things too seriously
我怕她鑽牛角尖
and gets herself into a dead end.
把自己給繞進去
I see.
我明白
You want me to comfort her.
你是想讓我去勸勸她
I'd appreciate it very much.
蘇某感激不盡
Su Mu, why do you thank me on behalf of Yuanyuan?
蘇沐 你為何要替長姐謝我
Her Highness once said that
這大郡主有句話
it doesn't matter where a hero comes from.
她說英雄不問出處
Although I am working at clan school now,
雖然蘇沐現在在宗學堂做事
but everyone who knows me
但見到我的人
regards me as a musician
無不想著我曾經身陷教坊司
from the Music and Dance Academy.
是個樂人
Only Her Highness
只有大郡主看我的眼神
regards me as an ordinary person.
與看旁人無異
That's right.
也是
You and Yuanyuan are indeed linked by ties of fate.
你與長姐 的確是有段緣分
That's not the case.
萬萬不敢
It's just that Her Highness and Your Highness felt compassion for me
是大郡主和三公主垂憐小人
and had a good opinion of me.
看得起小人罷了
Okay, I'll go and explain to Yuanyuan.
好了 我這就去找長姐解釋
Things are not as she heard them.
事情不是她聽到的那個樣子
I appreciate it very much. Your Highness.
謝過三公主
Yuanyuan. Yuanyuan.
長姐 長姐
Your Highness.
郡主
Didn't I tell you to stop her?
不是讓你攔著她嗎
If I want to come in, who dares to stop me?
我想進來 那誰敢攔著
Yuanyuan. What are you doing?
長姐 你這是在幹什麼
You don't want to take the test?
你要放棄擢考
As a worthless person,
一介廢人
I will only be ridiculed by the whole world no matter what.
無論如何只會被天下人恥笑
Isn't that what you said?
這不是你說過的話嗎
No, Yuanyuan.
不是的 長姐
I was talking about myself.
我那是在說我自己
It was none of your business.
跟你沒關係
Don't take it personally.
你可別這麼想你自己啊
It's my business to decide whether to take the test or not.
要不要參加擢考是我自己的事
You have no right to decide it for me.
我的事還輪不著你來指手畫腳
Your Highness, what are you doing?
三公主 您這是做什麼
Chen Qianqian.
陳芊芊
Are you humiliating me?
你是在羞辱我嗎
No. That's not the case.
不不不 不是這樣的
Yuanyuan, I'm caring about you.
長姐 我是心疼你
I don't want to see you give yourself up like this.
我不想看你這樣就放棄自己
Caring about me?
心疼我
I'm really caring about you.
我是真的心疼你
I've made some preparation.
我做準備了
I'm not kidding.
我不是說說而已
Look.
你看
This is what I've sorted out from a lot of books.
這是我從好多書裡面整理出來的
I've done it for some days.
已 已經準備有一些時日了
I've been planning
我在想著說
to give it to you when I get the chance.
找個機會就給你的
I don't know if it is useful.
我也不知道有沒有用
But perhaps these can help you
但也許這些能夠幫助你
to stand up again.
重新站起來
No matter how they work,
不管療效怎麼樣
you should try them.
你都試試看
You found these cures for me.
你為我找的療法
Do you think that
你是不是覺得
your medical skill is better than mine?
你的醫術比我更好
Your medical skill is absolutely good.
長 長姐的醫術自然高明
But for so many years
可這麼多年
you haven't given medical care to your legs.
你都不曾治自己的腿
Your Highness, please stop.
三公主 您快別說了
Because you don't dare to, do you?
因為你不敢 對不對
Because you are afraid that you cannot cure your legs.
因為你怕治不好
So over the years,
所以你這麼多年
you haven't tried
都沒有嘗試過
to let yourself stand up again.
讓自己重新站起來
You want to make me stand up again.
你讓我重新站起來
It's just like you want to win the Kung Fu test though you are unable to practice Kung Fu.
就如同武功盡失的你要贏得武試
Do you think it is possible?
你覺得 這可能嗎
You get out of here.
你走吧
Yuanyuan.
長姐
Your Highness, please go back.
三公主請回吧
Stop drinking.
別喝了
Zi Rui, why can't this wine make me drunk?
梓銳 這酒為什麼喝不醉呀
It's full of fruit juice inside.
這裡面裝的都是果子露
It's impossible to get drunk.
怎麼可能喝醉呢
What's more,
再說了
Young Master Han told me not to let you drink wine.
韓少君交代過 不讓你喝酒
Drinking wine is harmful to health.
喝酒傷身體
Why does Han Shuo want to dominate my life in every aspect?
這韓爍為什麼事事都要管著我
Eh...
那
Excuse me, Miss,
這位姑娘
what are you worrying about?
在為何事發愁啊
What are you gonna do by doing this?
你搞這幹什麼
I'm not a kid.
我又不是小孩子
It's my apology.
向你賠罪
Qianqian.
芊芊
Since you don't want to prepare for the test,
既然你不想複習考試
I won't push you anymore.
以後我不會逼你了
That's good.
那就好
What?
幹什麼
Don't you feel this doll
你不覺得有一個人偶
is much like you?
特別像你嗎
Yeah. It looks like me.
好像是
What about this one?
那這個呢
Who does it look like?
像誰
This...
這個
Sorry, I broke it.
對不起啊 斷了
It doesn't matter.
沒事
It'd be okay if I put its legs back.
把腿接上就好了
Legs cannot be put back again.
接不上了
It's all my fault.
都怪我
It's just a doll.
一個人偶而已
Why are you so sad?
為什麼這麼傷心啊
Did it ever occur to you that
你有沒有想過
for the common people,
對於普通百姓來講
we are at a dominating position which can never be reached.
我們是高不可攀的存在
Even a casual sentence
隨便一句話
can easily change someone's fate.
他人的命運就會輕易地改變
They are
他們
just like this clay figurine.
就像這個泥人
Something I've done before
以前我做了一些事情
easily changed someone else's fate.
輕而易舉地就決定了別人的命運
But I've never asked
可是我從來沒有問過
that person's idea and feeling.
別人的想法和心情
Ever since I was diagnosed with heart disease,
自從我診出心疾
I've visited famous doctors across the world.
訪遍天下名醫
They all said that I would die before 20.
都說我活不過二十歲
I had thought that
我原來以為
I would die like this in a foreign land.
我就要這麼客死異鄉了
But it never occurred to me that
可未曾想到的是
you appeared.
你出現了
It was you who got the Dragon Bone for me
是你為我求來龍骨
and cured my heart disease.
治癒心疾
Until then I came to realize that
至此我才明白
no one's fate is predestined.
誰的命運都不是生來就註定的
Perhaps all of it can be changed.
也許這一切都是可以改變的
Just like me.
正如我一樣
(Rehabilitation Guideline) You want to make me stand up again.
你讓我重新站起來
It's just like you want to win the Kung Fu test though you are unable to practice Kung Fu.
就如同武功盡失的你要贏得武試
Do you think it is possible?
你覺得 這可能嗎
Do you think that
那你覺得
I can win the Kung Fu test
武功盡失的我
though I'm unable to practice Kung Fu?
能贏得武試擢選嗎
Miss Lin Qi, you invited me out,
不知林七小姐找下官出來
what do you want from me?
所為何事
If Miss Lin Qi want me to do something,
林七小姐有何吩咐
you can just tell me.
儘管說便是
There's no need to present such a generous gift.
何必備來如此厚禮
I feel...
下官當真是
very embarrassed.
這怎麼好意思呢
Listen to me.
你聽好了
I want you to
我要你在武考之時
make Chen Qianqian fight against me at the Kung Fu test
不管如何地排位對陣
no matter what the agenda is.
只要讓陳芊芊與我比試
The Third Princess?
三公主
But...
這
It is just the deposit.
這些銀兩隻是定金
You'll absolutely
剩下的
get the rest.
自然少不了你的
I will go all out to do
林七小姐的吩咐
what you tell me to do.
下官自當全力以赴
I'm gonna fix her myself
我要親自收拾她
and bring disgrace on her publicly.
讓她在眾目睽睽之下出醜
I have good news and bad news.
我有一個好消息和一個壞消息
Which do you want to hear first?
你先聽哪一個
Bad news first.
壞的吧
Let me hear what news could be worse.
讓我聽聽還有什麼事能夠更壞
It's said that Lin Qi bought off the Kung Fu test officer.
聽聞 林七買通了武試官
She wanted to fight against you herself.
要親自與你一決高下
Since I've got myself into this situation,
都到這份兒上了
I don't think there's any good news.
還能有好的
The good news is
好消息是
I can let you win.
我能讓你贏
Your Highness, Your Highness.
三公主 三公主
My master doesn't want to meet any guest today.
我們主子今日著實不方便見客
I just want to say two sentences. Just two sentences.
我就說兩句話 就說兩句
Yuanyuan.
長姐
Your Highness, please go back.
三公主請回吧
Her Highness said that
郡主交代了
she doesn't want to see you recently.
最近不想見您
Yuanyuan.
長姐
I come here today just to ask you
我今天就是來想問問你
if I win
是不是隻要我贏得了
the Kung Fu test at the Crown Princess Election,
少城主擢考的武試
can you promise me to do rehabilitation training
你就答應我做復健
and make efforts to stand up again?
答應我重新試著站起來
Your Highness, please don't make things difficult for me.
公主別為難小的了
Her Highness won't see you today.
郡主今兒不會見您的
Yuanyuan.
長姐
Yuanyuan, if you don't say a word.
長姐 那你不說話
I take it as your acquiescence.
我就當作是你默認了
I'm telling you,
我告訴你
I'll surely win the Kung Fu test.
我一定可以贏得武試的
At that time you should not act shamelessly and deny it.
到時候你不要耍賴不認賬啊
Who on earth is acting shamelessly?
到底是誰在耍賴啊
Yuanyuan.
長姐
However hard it is, I will make it.
不管有什麼困難我都會做到的